<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Monorail Maniac - 3rd Party Elements</title><link href="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/feeds/3rd-party-elements.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.monorailmaniac.com/</id><updated>2025-10-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>3rd Party Elements</title><link href="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/3rd-party-elements.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-10-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-10-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>The Monorail Maniac</name></author><id>tag:www.monorailmaniac.com,2025-10-22:/3rd-party-elements.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Discussion of 3rd party (unofficial) elements.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;3rd Party Elements&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though The Lego Group discontinued official monorail part production in the early 90s, the advent of 3D printing has provided a new way to procure monorail elements. Designers have recreated classic monorail elements as well as a slew of new parts. Some of these new parts are based on designs detailed in the official patent applications while others are novel. These links are not sponsored and as of 10/22/2025 the Monorail Maniac has no affiliation with the sites - they are provided for informational purposes only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;4D Brix&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4D Brix is one of the most prolific designers of new monorail elements. They provide various stores which print their designs. ]Their monorail library](https://www.4dbrix.com/products/monorail/){:target="_blank"} is extensive, including track elements, train elements, and various accessories. Many elements are featured in videos on their &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/@4DBrix/videos" target="_blank"&gt;YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their track library includes a reproduction of the long and short straight track, and short left and right-hand turnouts. They also provide half-length and quarter-length straight track, a ramp extender section, two different diagonal track extensions (compatible with short curves), and a novel tile-height straight section along with a ramp to transition from regular track height to tile-height. Most interesting is their grade crossing element.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their train elements include a reproduction of the original motor cover, an updated motor cover with many additional studs, and two train extension cars (16 and 20 stud lengths).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The accessories include lights, motors, and motor brackets as well as 1x4 tiles to connect the track pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have handled some track printed on 4D Brix designs. I thought it was of reasonably high qualtity for a 3D print and trains traversed it with little trouble. I've seen the grade crossing and ramp extenders in person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Yeggi&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeggi is a 3D print library. Numerous track and train elements are linked. Many models are released under the Creative Commons 4.0 license. You can peruse the selection of elements &lt;a href="https://www.yeggi.com/q/lego+monorail/" target="_blank"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thingiverse&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thingiverse is another 3D print library. It features a few monorail track designs, but they all also appear on Yeggi (as of 10/23/2025). You can pruse Thingiverse's selection of elements &lt;a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/search?q=lego+monorail&amp;amp;page=1" target="_blank"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Printables&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Printables is yet another 3D print library. It has a wide variety of track and train elements including a wye design, large curves, and motors. You can check out the selection &lt;a href="https://www.printables.com/tag/monorail" target="&amp;quot;_blank"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="3rd Party Elements"></category><category term="custom elements"></category></entry></feed>