<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Monorail Maniac</title><link href="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.monorailmaniac.com/</id><updated>2025-10-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Monorail Element Info</title><link href="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/monorail-element-info.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-10-29T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-10-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>The Monorail Maniac</name></author><id>tag:www.monorailmaniac.com,2025-10-29:/monorail-element-info.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Descriptions of monorail elements and interesting facts.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Monorail Element Info&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core monorail system is comprised of track and train elements. I consider the 9V system (battery box, cables, and accessories) as its elements are usable outside of monorail. This list details the various monorail elements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Train elements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These elements are needed to assemble an official monorail train.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=bb1171c01#T=S&amp;amp;C=11&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:11,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;Monorail Wheel on Axle (bb1171c01)&lt;/a&gt; - Wheelset mounted on metal axle. The axle is too small for a minifig to hold. Two of these axles are inserted into the bogie to hold a train car and allow it to move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2686#T=S&amp;amp;C=11&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:11,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;Monorail Bogie (2686)&lt;/a&gt; - The bogie is the frame which holds the wheels. It is combined with a bracket (fork) to allow the wheels to move independent of the train car frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2697#T=S&amp;amp;C=11&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:11,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;Monorail Bracket/Pivot/Fork&lt;/a&gt; - A U-shaped piece with clips on the ends an a Technic half-height pin on top. This element attaches the train car base to the bogie and allows for movement of the bogie back and forth as well as tilt up and down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2687#T=S&amp;amp;C=11&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:11,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;Monorail Base (Train Car Frame)&lt;/a&gt; - The body on which a train car can be assembled. One end has an attachment point for a bogie (fork) and the other has a coupler designed to attach to a monorail motor coupler. The base is 4x20 studs in size and has a 2x2 section raised one plate high with a central hole starting 4 studs back and 1 stud in where the bogie's fork attaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monorail Coupler &lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2685a#T=S&amp;amp;C=11&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:11,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;Short (2685a)&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2685b#T=S&amp;amp;C=11&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:11,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;Long (2685b)&lt;/a&gt; - A bent U-shaped coupler with clips on the both ends and a groove in the center. This element serves to couple a motor with a car. The end clips provide vertical motion to the car while the groove allows the car side-to-side motion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monorail Motor &lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2684c01a#T=S&amp;amp;O={%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;with Short Couplings (2684c01a)&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2684c01b#T=S&amp;amp;C=1&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:1,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;with Long Couplings (2684c01b)&lt;/a&gt; - The 9V motor which drives the train. It has a coupler on either end so it can attach two cars. It has a cylindrical body with cutout sides. The body curve does not match any standard Lego cylinder. There is a 2x2 square of four studs on top and two 2x2 stud square protrusions each facing one coupler. One of the 2x2 side protrusions has metal contacts for connecting the 9V system. The motor has four wheels. A rocker switch on the bottom can protrude from either or both sides of the motor. When the rocker is centered the motor does not move. The motor always moves to the right of the direction in which the rocker switch protrudes. That is, if you are facing the motor and the switch is pushed towards you the motor will begin moving to the left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2619#T=S&amp;amp;C=5&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:5,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;Monorail Motor Cover (2619)&lt;/a&gt; - Generally square cover. Covers almost the entire motor, but leaves the couplers, rocker switch, and both 2x2 side protrusions exposed. A 2x8 line of studs longways runs atop the cover. Both top sides of the cover are recessed by 1 plate and have a 3x4 set of studs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Track elements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These elements provide a surface for the train to run on and have a rack the motor engages for movement. All track elements have a 1x2 section on either side of the end with which to connect other track pieces. All track elements also have a 1x2 antistud section on either end and a 2x2 antistud section located approximately in the center of the piece to attach stanchions/supports. The flat surface on every track element is 1 LDU higher than a stack of platse would be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2670#T=S&amp;amp;C=9&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:9,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;Monorail Short Straight (2670)&lt;/a&gt; - A straight piece of track which can fit a monorail motor on top. This is the smallest monorail track piece at only 8 studs long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2671#T=S&amp;amp;C=9&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:9,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;Monorail Long Straight (2671)&lt;/a&gt; - A straight piece of track which can fit a monorail motor and car on top. This is the longest straight piece of track available with a length of 32 studs (equivalent to four short straight pieces).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2677#T=S&amp;amp;C=9&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:9,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;Monorail Ramp Lower (2677)&lt;/a&gt; - A straight piece of track which curves upwards. The upper end has an angled slope which only mates with the monorail ramp upper. Has a length of 32 studs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2678#T=S&amp;amp;C=9&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:9,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;Monorail Ramp Upper (2678)&lt;/a&gt; - A straight piece of track which curves from a slope to level. The lower end has an angled slope which only mates with the monorail ramp lower. Has a length of 32 studs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2772c01#T=S&amp;amp;C=9&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:9,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;Monorail Stop/Go Switch (2772c01)&lt;/a&gt; - A straight piece of track which has a stop/go element attached. Has a length of 16 studs. The stop/go element is placed 2 studs back from one end of the track. The stop/go element is 4x12 studs in size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monorail Turnout &lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2889#T=S&amp;amp;C=9&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:9,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;Right (2889)&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2890#T=S&amp;amp;C=9&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:9,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;Left (2890)&lt;/a&gt; - A 32 stud long element which allows trains to diverge from the straight track. The divergent end has another unique shape so it can only mate with out turnout pieces or half curves. The track is designed to automatically align the switch if a train approaches from a direction which is not set. A manually throw is also included for manipulating the turnout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monorail Short Curve &lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2891#T=S&amp;amp;C=9&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:9,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;Right (2891)&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2892#T=S&amp;amp;C=9&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:9,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;Left (2892)&lt;/a&gt; - A curve which is half the length of a regular large curve. One end has a special shape to only mate with other cruves or turnouts. Can be used to create an S-bend, a 90° turnout from a straight track, or a parallel track (depending with which element it is combined).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2672#T=S&amp;amp;C=9&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:9,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;Monorail Large Curve (2672)&lt;/a&gt; - A full 90° curve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Resources"></category><category term="elements"></category><category term="parts"></category><category term="pieces"></category></entry><entry><title>Set List</title><link href="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/set-list.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-10-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-10-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>The Monorail Maniac</name></author><id>tag:www.monorailmaniac.com,2025-10-27:/set-list.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Descriptions of the monorail system sets.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Monorail Set List&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The monorail system consisted of three traditional sets (those complete with trains, minifigures, and stations), two track expansion kits, and two service packs. The system lasted from 1987-1994 and spanned three three themes - Futuron, Airport, and Unitron. A brief description and review of each set will be included here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;6990 Futuron Monorail (released 1987)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This 715 piece set is the Futuron theme's flagship. The set features two detailed bases, a play feature rich train, and various other accessories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Futuron monorail train design is considered by many to be the best amongst the three official trains. This monorail sports seating for three, storage for a skiff, removable cargo container, and a unique removable battery box. The removable containers can be hauled by a small cargo ship or handled by machinery at either of the two included bases. The train has an angular design which fit perfectly with the rest of the Futuron theme. Perhaps the most striking feature is the insulator-like protrusions on the front circled by hoses. The motor decoration is basic with a pair of trans-dark blue 1x1 round plates and a 2x2 dish. This set was the only large set to include a motor with short couplers (the other short coupler set being a service pack).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This set's layout is a basic loop with hill. Each station has a stop/go switch, but what really makes this layout stand out is the trackside equipment. There are two track-mounted dishes and a track mounted scanner loop. This is the only set to use the studs on the side of the track to attach trackside equipment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each base included with the set includes a significant play feature. Half of the dome base rotates to move a sled into place beside the track. This sled can hold one of the train's removable containers. The raised base includes an elevator which is also designed to hold a container. Various control panels and other printed bricks compliment the greebles on both bases to round out the aesthetic. The set also includes five minifigures and a small cargo spaceship to haul containers around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a space builder this is my favorite monorail set. The train is as cool as a spaceship - it hauls a scooter, cargo, and figs. The base buildings are interesting and interactive. The set oozes character from the train to the buildings to the trackside equipment. I highly recommend everyone peruse &lt;a href="https://lego.brickinstructions.com/lego_instructions/set/6990/Monorail_Transport_System" target="_blank"&gt;the instructions&lt;/a&gt; if not outright buy the set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;5039 Monorail Stop/Reverse Switch Service Pack (released 1987)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This 3 piece service pack provided a way to add additional stops to a monorail layout. The set includes the stop/go piece, a 2x2 round brick, and a 2x2 printed arrow tile. This assembly matches the switches as used in set 6990. The service pack was the only monorail set released in a bag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;6921 Monorail Accessory Track (released 1988)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 46 piece monorail accessory track set was the first opportunity for owners of set 6990 to dramatically increase their layout size. The set featured additional straight track, curves, and supports with two different heights. This expansion included a insert suggesting various layout designs one could build when combining the kit with 6990. Even the back of the box visualized a layout when combined with 6990. Another interesting box detail was the inclusion of a ghostly outline of a train on the track - this would not be seen again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An interesting aside is that in &lt;a href="https://buildingdebates.wordpress.com/2017/04/29/bjarne-tveskov/" target="_blank"&gt;an interview with Building Debates&lt;/a&gt; former Lego designer Bjarne Panduro Tveskov mentioned writing software for the Sinclair QL to simulate track layouts combining 6990 and 6921.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;5040 Monorail 9V Motor (released 1988)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5040 is the only single piece service pack released specifically for the monorail system and the only way to acquire a motor outside one of the larger sets. This motor had short couplings, just like the one included in 6990.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This service pack seems like it was intended to allow owners of a set to replace a damaged motor rather than add a second train to their layout. I believe this because a battery box and cable would also have to be bought separately for the motor to be used in a second train. Also, since the monorail cars were not available separately the existing train would need to be split up to make a train for the new motor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;6399 Airport Shuttle (released 1990)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 728 piece Airport Shuttle is the largest monorail set by both sheer part count and by monorail element count. This behemouth is also the only non-space entry in the monorail portfolio. It includes the only official monorail engine cover ever released.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The train is a straightforward &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/People_mover" target="_blank"&gt;people mover&lt;/a&gt; with seating for five plus two operators. The passenger cabins are separated from the driver cabs by a piece of glass. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gull-wing_door" target="_blank"&gt;Gull-wing doors&lt;/a&gt; provide access to the passenger cabins, but this does require the train to face a specific direction so the figs can reach the platforms. Perhaps the most interesting (and I think unfortunate) design choice is the battery box being integrated directly into the train itself. Thus, changing the battery requires disassembling one of the train cars. The engine cover works well to blend the train together seemlessly and adds some vent detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The set includes two stations - one intended to be near the airport terminal and the other in downtown. Both stations include raised platforms with ticket machines as well as signals for the monorail. The airport station conveniently includes seating, a flight schedule, and luggage storage bins. A beautifully designed "T" built into the station roof mirrors the logo sported by the train. There is a dropoff location where taxis can deposit passengers for the station or continue on to the airport. A payphone across the street from the station is likely to confuse those born after the year 2000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The downtown station is raised high above a track running below. It includes a flight schedule, airport map, and a few seats. It's a hike to get up to! A hamburger stand underneath it provides a place for busy travelers to grab a snack. A few streetlights mounted underneath the station are a nice touch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm a space guy so this review may be biased, sorry all you Town and City folks! Despite being large, I don't find this set particularly exciting. It seems the part budget was spent on including a large amount of track rather than maximizing play features. There are some nice details, such as the ticket machines and lights, but there's not much for the minifigs to do. They can grab a hamburger, wait at the station, and ride the train. That probably excites some people, but the set really seems like it needs other Town or Airport sets for a fun experience. The set is a great monorail parts pack, but it's the last monorail I would set up if I wanted to sit down and have some fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;6347 Monorail Accessory Track (released 1991)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second track expansion kit was the first time monorail turnouts were made available. This 54 piece kit included a left and right turnout, two straights, curves, and stanchions. The set included an insert showing a few layouts that could be made by combining the kit with 6990 or 6399. The sides of the box showed layouts with both sets as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;6991 Monorail Transport Base (released 1994)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 555 piece monorail transport base is the last entry in the monorail system and the flagship Unitron base. It includes a complex track layout, three stations, and numerous cool play features. It is a fitting end to the monorail line (pun intended).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The train is unique in that it does not have a permanent cab. Rather, the train hauls two Unitron spaceships (or perhaps just spaceship cockpits - depends on your imagination) which double as cabs for the train. The battery box is mounted directly on the car base, but the train does not require significant disassembly to remove it. There are various Unitron-style greebles, but the train design does seem a little sparse. The cars are designed to allow the spaceships to slide off the end (more on that in a bit).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The track layout includes a loop at 10-brick height. Two spurs diverge from the loop. Both turn inside the loop before one soars above the loop and the other drops below it. This is the only large monorail set to include turnouts. One spur ends atop a control center built on a mountain or rocky pillar. Here the spaceship on the train is pushed onto a platform and a trackside mechanism automatically reverses the train. The other spur ends at ground level where a truck can be placed to receive the spaceship off the train before it is reversed by a stop/go track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main station is built on a raised baseplate. It has a few neat features. A satellite dish on an axle is turned by the train when it passes via a wheel placed at a strategic level. The base also features an arm which can swing between train cars to carry a spaceship from one end of the train to another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three Unitron figs and a Spyrius droid were included to man the set. A truck capable of hauling a spaceship was also included. It sported a detachable "cab" that could double as a skiff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall this is my second favorite full monorail set. It shows off quite a few cool techniques including the mountaintop automatic monorail reverser, the train-to-ground transfer mechanism, the train-to-truck transfer mechanism, and the rotating satellite dish. The set has the most interesting layout of any official monorail set. It also boasts more play features than 6399. However, the set feels more anemic than 6990. While it sports quite a few greebles, they're less visually coherent than those found on the older set. Many greebles are simply antennas and satellite dishes. The train exemplefies the emphasis on engineering over aesthetic as the ingenious unloading mechanism is paired with a scantly decorated battery box and motor while the other train car sports what appears to be a spaceship engine affixed permanently to the car. I encourage any collector to review this set and seriously consider purchasing it as it is fun to play with despite its minor flaws.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Resources"></category><category term="sets"></category></entry><entry><title>Interesting Projects</title><link href="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/interesting-ideas.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-10-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-10-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>The Monorail Maniac</name></author><id>tag:www.monorailmaniac.com,2025-10-26:/interesting-ideas.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Interesting ideas and monorail projects.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Interesting Projects&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The official monorail sets presented the system in a straightforward way. They consisted of basic loops (and spurs) with two or three bases. The trains all used the same basic structure with a central motor flanked by monorail car bases. The Unitron monorail was the most interesting as the cars hauled ships which could be offloaded onto a launch platform or on a truck and the base had an antenna which would rotate as the train passed. Here I'll share a few interesting projects and ideas I've had which stretch the system a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Motor-Only train (Spyrius Monorail)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the official trains all included two bogies, two monorail bases, a motor, a power cable, and a 9V battery box. I quickly realized that in reality a train or, more specifically, an engine only required a motor, power cable, and battery box. My first attempt at building such a train saw the battery box perched atop the motor with a cab for the driver placed on an arm which could swing around the motor to either side so the driver could always face forward. It was extremely top heavy and struggled to even navigate curves. Hills were out of the question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My second design was a Spyrius robot. I used the monorail motor cover to shroud the motor then added the battery box across the top perpendicular to the rail. I built a body around this basic design with arms and a seat for the driver on the very top. This robot works well on level track and navigates turns with ease. Hills are still out of the question as it is also top heavy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Spyrius Monorail" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/spyrius_monorail.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may be possible to navigate hills if the battery box were mounted on the end studs with a counterweight on the opposite side of the motor, but I have not seriously tried this yet. Let me know if you do!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Handcar&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Handcars are one of the most iconic vehicles in railroading. Sure, they haven't been used for probably close to a century, but they're still cool. I built a spacey handcar using just a bogie. It even "worked" - if you pushed down on one end and let it "pop" up it would wobble forward and backward and move down a straight section of track. I've since torn the model apart, but hopefully you can try something similar!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Monorail handcar" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/handcar.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Automatic Block Signaling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running multiple trains on a monorail layout can be difficult since the trains can run at different speeds depending on the strength of their battery. I used to work for a company who made signaling systems for railroads so I was inspired to create an Automatic Block Signaling system (ABS) for monorail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My prototype used an RCX brick, an old 9V motor, and a light sensor. The RCX brick would use the light sensor to determine if a block (protected section of track) was occupied and, if so, set the monorail stop/go switch to the stop position. Once the light sensor showed nothing in the block the RCX brick would power the motor to set the stop/go switch to go. This system could be replicated over any number of blocks to ensure a slow train was never rear-ended by a more nimble compatriot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have not yet built a large permanent layout, but when I do I plan to incorporate ABS on the mainline portions to allow unsupervised multi-train operation. In this picture you can see the prototype with the stop/go set to stop since there is a minifig on the track!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Monorail Automatic Block Signaling" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/automatic_block_signaling.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Dump cars&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the first things I wanted to do after getting a monorail train was break free of the monorail base. It is a nifty piece and makes building trains a snap, but it is limiting. I quickly began experimenting with bogies attached directly to Technic plates. I also quickly began using magnetic couplers as they provided great flexibility and allowed cars to be uncoupled easily. I later discovered that the 6990 box included a monorail rollercoaster design on the back which used just a bogie without the monorail base to create the rollercoaster train (&lt;a href="https://www.backoftheboxbuilds.com/6990-back-b/" target="_blank"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; is the design).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An early attempt at such a car was an ore hauler which could be dumped by a trackside arm. The car itself had two bogies an early magnetic coupler attempt. An trackside arm could be lowered to tilt the V-shaped body and dump the cargo. This early design never worked well as the car would often tip off the track. The coupler mechanism also did not work well when navigating curves. I've since greatly improved my car designs, but here is an early example for inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Monorail dump car prototype" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/dumping_car_1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here is another attempt at a dumping design intended to be driven by an overhead gear rack:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Monorail dump car second prototype" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/dumping_car_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Monorail dump car second prototype dumping" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/dumping_car_3.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Inclined Plane&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inclined planes were used in the late 19th and early 20th century to connect low-lying cities with suburbs on the heights. A famous example is the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duquesne_Incline" target="_blank"&gt;Duquesne Incline&lt;/a&gt; in Pittsburgh, PA. The monorail system is suited to building an incline due to the cog design of the train.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I build an incline prototype at approximately a 45° angle. The train design is very important. I created a rigid connection between the monorail motor and a single monorail base which I placed uphill from the motor. I placed a battery box and boat weight pieces on the monorail base to keep the motor's cog engaged with the rail. I found that the motor was able to push the train up the slope fine and that the train did not need put in reverse at the top. Rather, when the motor was placed in neutral/stop the weight of the train pushed the engine slowly down the hill. Note that it is possible this would damage the battery long term since the motor was likely generating an electric current when being pushed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't have a picture of the entire working model, but I have a picture of a part of the track and one of a partially complete train.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Monorail inclined plane track" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/inclined_plane_track.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Monorail inclined plane train" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/inclined_plane_train.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One imagined use is as a shuttle to load ore in a large blast furnace or something similar. Let me know if you build an inclined plane!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outdoor Monorail Displays&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monorail is a great system to use outdoors. The large supports work well to elevate the track above grass and rocks while natural backgrounds can lead to some beautiful photographs. Perhaps my favorite monorail to date was the Ice Planet monorail train I built and set up in the snow. The plow on the engine actually worked!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ice Planet monorail on the track" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/ice_planet_monorail_1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ice Planet monorail approaches the hill" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/ice_planet_monorail_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ice Planet monorail enters the snow" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/ice_planet_monorail_3.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ice Planet monorail snow plow in action" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/ice_planet_monorail_4.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here is a shot of some spacemen in the grasslands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Space crew in the grasslands" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/outdoor_display_grass.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Custom Stop and Reverser Tracks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop/go switches are nice for stations, but when you just need an emergency stop at the end of a spur they're overkill. It's possible to build a custom stop track (or a custom reverser) using only a few basic pieces. Here is an example colored to show the various elements used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Custom monorail stop device" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/custom_stop_1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1x4 curves gently push the motor switch to the centeral stop position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Custom monorail stop device" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/custom_stop_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same basic concept can be used to force the switch in another direction to reverse the train, as seen in &lt;a href="https://lego.brickinstructions.com/lego_instructions/set/6991/Monorail_Transport_Base" target="_blank"&gt;6991 Monorail Transport Base&lt;/a&gt; (see the slope starting on step 14 and note the 2x3 plate with hole added on top).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Monorail Track Scale&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Real railroads sometimes have scale tracks customers use to weigh the product being delivered, such as scrap steel. Modeling one in monorail is difficult due to the rigidity of the track, but it's not impossible. The joints where monorail track is connected actually allows the track to flex a bit. The trick is converting this flexing into output which can be used to display a value. When I built my scale track I used some shock absorber pieces to ensure the track remained level when no train is on it. I then placed a bar under the track which pushes an arm. The end of the arm moves and points to a "tonnage" value on a wall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Monorail track scale support" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/track_scale_support.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Monorail track scale arm" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/track_scale_arm.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Monorail track scale complete" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/track_scale_complete.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may have an idea for a totally different design - I'd love to see it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Seatron monorail&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just because the Seatron theme was never officially released doesn't mean you can't build the train! I reverse engineered the design as best I could - there is also apparently an LDD or Stud.io file available somewhere online. Almost every piece seen in the prototype image was released - I only identified three elements which were not released in the color used on the prototype. My train used yellow triple curve panels with stickers as they're cheaper to acquire in the US, but stickers can be removed!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Seatron reverse engineered" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/seatron_reverse_engineered_1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;![Seatron reverse engineered with some cargo doors open] ({static}/images/interesting-projects/seatron_reverse_engineered_2.jpg)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Monorail Bridge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another interesting feature to add to a layout is a bridge. A single piece of monorail track is strong, but if you want to bridge a large gap you quickly find the track flexing a bit too much. There are many ways to build bridges so I'll just present one design here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used the Nexagon piece released years ago to create a visually interesting design. The element design creates a line that parallels the track. The vertical spikes allow the track to be attached at a few points while providing an interesting detail below the bridge. The bridge is designed to be elevated with supports on both ends (so most of the bottom protrusions would be hanging in the air). Pillars could also be added below the structure if desired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Monorail nexagon bridge" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/bridge_assembled.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Monorail nexagon bridge detail" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/bridge_detail.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also experimented with a sandwiched plate bridge design that created a 2x2 structure directly below the track. The bridge used two 2x plates on either side of finger hinges laid on their side to create a strong core. The plates were tied together with brackets. The design looked something like a beam directly underneath the track. If I find a picture of this design I will add it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Custom cars&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've mentioned custom cars in ealier entries. I thought I'd also include a more modern design. This car uses magnet couplers mounted on a 2x2 swivel and using a Technic plate w/ pin holder to allow maximum flexibility. The car frame uses a pair of Technic bricks with half pins to attach the side plates. The bogies are attached with Technic plates and a combination of Technic elements and finger hinges are used to assemble the sides and deck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Custom monorail car" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/custom_car.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Streamlined train&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Streamlined &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EMD_F-unit" target="_blank"&gt;F-Units&lt;/a&gt; are some of the most famous railroad engines of all time. They inspired me to create a streamlined monorail train. The body consists primarily of curved panels with some grills and other greebles added for aesthetic purposes. I call the train The Thunderbolt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Thunderbolt side profile" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/thunderbolt_1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Thunderbolt front" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/thunderbolt_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Thunderbolt cab" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/thunderbolt_3.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I may revisit the design someday to streamline the cab domes as well. See what kind of streamlining you can do with monorail!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Interactive Trackside elements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having the train drive action along the track (or the track drive action on the train) is another interesting idea and one I encourage you to explore. My experiments have used racks and gears to interface between the train and trackside infrastructure. I did not use the same technique as seen in 6991 for two reasons: my trains tend to not be smooth on the side and, more importantly, I want to be able to control which cars drive the action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an example trackside satellite dish which can be driven by a train, a train equiped to drive it (and equiped to be driven by trackside racks), and an example showing both trackside gears and racks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Monorail trackside satellite dish" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/trackside_dish.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Monorail with trackside interfaces" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/trackside_train.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Monorail trackside equipment" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/trackside_gears_and_rack.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another, more ambitious, goal for this system is driving an automatic car unloader. I'd like a train to drive by some trackside racks that automatically drive the dumping mechanism on the cars. Racks on the train could drive gears and allow the cars to be automatically reloaded elsewhere on the layout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Trackside Industries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The official sets all included stations for the trains to interact with. My layouts usually have more industries than stations. Industries allow opportunities for switching and more realistic train moves. Here is a basic space tank farm with equipment to load and unload tank cars. Note the buffer at the end of the track - this was before I built permanent stop elements!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Monorail transloading facility" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/transloading_facility_with_buffer.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Intra-Meteor Car Hauler&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Rusty Orion ship built for SHIPtember was an interesting idea. The intention was a ferry to move monorail trains between meteors which were being mined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Rusty Orion top" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/rusty_orion_1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Rusty Orion angle" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/rusty_orion_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Rusty Orion side" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/interesting-projects/rusty_orion_3.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Other inspiration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few other ideas to explore, in no particular order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mobile orbital defense laser&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Firefighting monorail&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sea serpent and/or underwater monorail&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Food truck themed monorail train&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ferry (load monorail cars on a boat that really floats!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A knight's joust using trains as the horses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Portage railroad (railroad designed to haul boats over mountains that canals cannot easily cross)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mine train (perhaps a low clearance design)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Projects"></category><category term="ideas"></category><category term="projects"></category></entry><entry><title>3rd Party Elements</title><link href="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/3rd-party-elements.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-10-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-10-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>The Monorail Maniac</name></author><id>tag:www.monorailmaniac.com,2025-10-22:/3rd-party-elements.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Discussion of 3rd party (unofficial) elements.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;3rd Party Elements&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though The Lego Group discontinued official monorail part production in the early 90s, the advent of 3D printing has provided a new way to procure monorail elements. Designers have recreated classic monorail elements as well as a slew of new parts. Some of these new parts are based on designs detailed in the official patent applications while others are novel. These links are not sponsored and as of 10/22/2025 the Monorail Maniac has no affiliation with the sites - they are provided for informational purposes only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;4D Brix&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4D Brix is one of the most prolific designers of new monorail elements. They provide various stores which print their designs. ]Their monorail library](https://www.4dbrix.com/products/monorail/){:target="_blank"} is extensive, including track elements, train elements, and various accessories. Many elements are featured in videos on their &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/@4DBrix/videos" target="_blank"&gt;YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their track library includes a reproduction of the long and short straight track, and short left and right-hand turnouts. They also provide half-length and quarter-length straight track, a ramp extender section, two different diagonal track extensions (compatible with short curves), and a novel tile-height straight section along with a ramp to transition from regular track height to tile-height. Most interesting is their grade crossing element.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their train elements include a reproduction of the original motor cover, an updated motor cover with many additional studs, and two train extension cars (16 and 20 stud lengths).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The accessories include lights, motors, and motor brackets as well as 1x4 tiles to connect the track pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have handled some track printed on 4D Brix designs. I thought it was of reasonably high qualtity for a 3D print and trains traversed it with little trouble. I've seen the grade crossing and ramp extenders in person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Yeggi&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeggi is a 3D print library. Numerous track and train elements are linked. Many models are released under the Creative Commons 4.0 license. You can peruse the selection of elements &lt;a href="https://www.yeggi.com/q/lego+monorail/" target="_blank"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thingiverse&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thingiverse is another 3D print library. It features a few monorail track designs, but they all also appear on Yeggi (as of 10/23/2025). You can pruse Thingiverse's selection of elements &lt;a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/search?q=lego+monorail&amp;amp;page=1" target="_blank"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Printables&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Printables is yet another 3D print library. It has a wide variety of track and train elements including a wye design, large curves, and motors. You can check out the selection &lt;a href="https://www.printables.com/tag/monorail" target="&amp;quot;_blank"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="3rd Party Elements"></category><category term="custom elements"></category></entry><entry><title>Advertising</title><link href="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/advertising.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-10-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-10-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>The Monorail Maniac</name></author><id>tag:www.monorailmaniac.com,2025-10-07:/advertising.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Various monorail advertisements.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Advertisements&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many late 80s and early 90s advertisements featured the monorail system. Various examples are linked here (links confirmed active as of 10/7/2025).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Comic&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://spacethecomic.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/rymd_1987.jpg" target="_blank"&gt;Lego 6990 featured in Commander Black comic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Shopvideo Advertisements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=w4w5YsNm5qk&amp;amp;t=216s" target="_blank"&gt;Lego 6921 in 1988 Lego Shopvideo (timestamp 3:39)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/_miHaJbXv48?si=_-qgtLZ95X8U94nN&amp;amp;t=445" target="_blank"&gt;Lego 6990 in 1989 Lego Shopvideo (timestamp 7:25)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SRHqQnsqZUU" target="_blank"&gt;Lego 6990 being rescued by M:Tron in 1990 Shopvideo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DDfbIQP9g-E&amp;amp;t=251s" target="_blank"&gt;Lego 6399 in 1991 Lego Shopvideo (timestamp 4:11)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DDfbIQP9g-E&amp;amp;t=592s" target="_blank"&gt;Rube Goldberg creation including monorail, 1991 Lego Shopvideo (timestamp 9:52)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Television Advertisements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cusvoOu3rYw" target="_blank"&gt;Spyrius vs Unitron television advertisement (6991)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/puCuJPCM8ms?si=WuI91VGQeI_pty7s&amp;amp;t=278" target="_blank"&gt;(Another) Spyrius vs Unitron television advertisement (6991)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Catalogs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?C=c87se&amp;amp;name=1987%20Medium%20Swedish%20(920313-S.)&amp;amp;category=%5B1987%5D#T=S&amp;amp;O={%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;1987 "flying" monorail&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?C=m87nl2&amp;amp;name=1987%20Mini%20Dutch%20(150606-NL)&amp;amp;category=%5B1987%5D#T=S&amp;amp;O={%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;1987 "moonbase" monorail&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?C=c87be2&amp;amp;name=1987%20Medium%20Belgian&amp;amp;category=%5B1987%5D#T=S&amp;amp;O={%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;1987 "soaring" monorail&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?C=m88ussp&amp;amp;name=1988%20Mini%20Space%20(100717-US)&amp;amp;category=%5B1988%5D%5BSpace%5D#T=S&amp;amp;O={%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;1988 Futuron base&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?C=m89eusp&amp;amp;name=1989%20Mini%20Space%20European%20(108483-EU)&amp;amp;category=%5B1989%5D%5BSpace%5D#T=S&amp;amp;O={%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;1988 Futuron with Space Police&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?C=m89ussp&amp;amp;name=1989%20Mini%20Space%20US%20(109417-US)&amp;amp;category=%5B1989%5D%5BSpace%5D#T=S&amp;amp;O={%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;1989 train robbery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?C=m90osto&amp;amp;name=1990%20Mini%20Town%20Overseas%20(113185-OS)&amp;amp;category=%5B1990%5D%5BTown%5D%5BClassic%20Town%5D#T=S&amp;amp;O={%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;1990 monorail by harbor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?C=m90ussp&amp;amp;name=1990%20Mini%20Space%20(114117-US)&amp;amp;category=%5B1990%5D%5BSpace%5D#T=S&amp;amp;O={%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;1990 M:Tron tunnel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?C=m91townus&amp;amp;name=1991%20Mini%20Town%20(832317-US)&amp;amp;category=%5B1991%5D%5BTown%5D%5BClassic%20Town%5D#T=S&amp;amp;O={%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;1991 monorail bridge over harbor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?C=m92usto&amp;amp;name=1992%20Mini%20Town%20US%20(103317-US)&amp;amp;category=%5B1992%5D%5BTown%5D%5BClassic%20Town%5D#T=S&amp;amp;O={%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;1992 airport monorail&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?C=m94nasp&amp;amp;name=1994%20Mini%20Space%20North%20America%20(996617-NA)&amp;amp;category=%5B1994%5D%5BSpace%5D#T=S&amp;amp;O={%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;1994 Spyrius attacking Unitron 6991&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?C=m94ossp&amp;amp;name=1994%20Mini%20Space%20Overseas%20(998685-OS)&amp;amp;category=%5B1994%5D%5BSpace%5D#T=S&amp;amp;O={%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;1994 Spyrius attacking Unitron 6991 (w/ play feature highlight)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?C=m95space&amp;amp;name=1995%20Mini%20Space%20(4.100.044-EU/OS)&amp;amp;category=%5B1995%5D%5BSpace%5D#T=S&amp;amp;O={%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;1995 Spyrius attacking Unitron 6991&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Advertising"></category><category term="advertising"></category></entry><entry><title>Prototypes and Unreleased Sets</title><link href="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/prototypes.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-10-06T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-10-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>The Monorail Maniac</name></author><id>tag:www.monorailmaniac.com,2025-10-06:/prototypes.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A brief overview of unreleased monorail prototypes.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Prototypes and Unreleased Sets&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagining what could have been is always exciting. Luckily, a little bit of information has surfaced offering a peek into experiments Lego designers performed with the system over the years. While it's unfortunate that these ideas did not make it to market, they can still inspire us!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Jacobs Bogie&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lego monorail Jacob bogie" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/prototypes/jacob_bogie.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the least surprising item on this list is the Jacobs bogie which appears in figure 12 of the US4861306A patent. I have personally handled this piece. It is the same size as monorail motor bogie and uses the same couplers. It sports four studs. A &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacobs_bogie" target="_blank"&gt;Jacobs bogie&lt;/a&gt; is shared between two railcars. The benefit of this arrangement is reduced friction since its use replaces two bogies with one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Seatron Monorail&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Seatron monorail set" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/prototypes/seatron.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Seatron monorail is the most well-known monorail prototype. It was first revealed in the "The Truth About SPACE!" article in &lt;a href="https://twomorrows.com/index.php?main_page=product_info&amp;amp;products_id=781" target="_blank"&gt;BrickJournal issue 6 volume 2&lt;/a&gt;. The monorail bogies and bases appear to match the released versions. There are some interesting recolors in the yellow motor, blue lower ramp, and blue large curve (see image below). The upper ramp could be painted or printed - likely a light gray base with blue added. The track supports are also all blue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Blue monorail curve" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/prototypes/blue_monorail_curve.jpg" width="250px"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently the monorail was going to be central to the theme. It was going to connect underwater astronauts or aliens with spaceships via the platform in the picture. Since the other monorail sets had underperformed the plan was scrapped and the theme morphed into Aquazone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Wild West Monorail&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Wild west monorail prototype" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/prototypes/wild_west.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least two monorail steam trains were designed while the Wild West theme was being prototyped. This was an odd choice since the traditional Lego train system was available. The prototype photo shows two black motors, two black straight tracks, one black upper ramp, and what is probably a black short right curve. Interestingly, the monorail base used under the passenger car appears to be 18 studs long rather than the 20 studs used in the system which was released. There do not appear to be battery boxes, but it is possible the trains were not intended to actually run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some other interesting details include the use of printed dishes as wheels, the driving rod design on the yellow and red loco, the printed 2x2 corner slope cow catchers, and the stickers decorating the upper loco.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Martian Monorail&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the mid-2010s I came across an online discussion regarding what happened to the monorail system. I have since lost the link, but that someone purporting to be Lego designer stated a martian themed monorail had been playtested in the late 90s (perhaps as part of what would become the Life on Mars theme). The design performed poorly. This was the last attempt to get a monorail set produced that I could find. The time period given roughly corresponds to the July 14th, 1999 date when the last renewal fee was paid on the monorail patents. Unfortunately, I have not been able to further corroborate the story.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Prototypes"></category><category term="prototypes-and-unreleased-sets"></category></entry><entry><title>Patents</title><link href="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/patents.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-10-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-10-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>The Monorail Maniac</name></author><id>tag:www.monorailmaniac.com,2025-10-05:/patents.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Details regarding the various patents covering the monorail system.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Monorail Patents&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The monorail system was protected by a collection of patents all of which have expired in the US. The basic track element patents (straight track, curves, and the monoswitch) were filed first followed shortly by the track system (what I call the "geometry") patent. A patent covering the motors, bogies, and other railcar elements followed about six months later. The last relevant patent covering the various turnout designs followed three years later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can learn a lot about the design of the system by reviewing these documents. Did you know a suspended monorail similar to the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wuppertal_Schwebebahn" target="_blank"&gt;Wuppertal Schwebebahn&lt;/a&gt; was considered? Figure 35 from US4861306A shows just such a design! And at figures 36a-h to see various track profiles which were considered (36a is the profile which was ultimately released). Another interesting idea was the integration of magnet couplers directly on the bogies (figures 26 &amp;amp; 28). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first patent was filed on November 26th, 1986. Fees were regularly paid for many years. The last renewal fees  were paid July 14th, 1999 after which the fees were unpaid and the patents expired. It seems by around 2000 the system had been completely written off as a viable part of the Lego company's portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The patents are available in the &lt;a href="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/files/Monorail-Maniac-Patent-Pack.zip"&gt;Patent Pack&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Element&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;US Patent&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Filing Date&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img alt="Trains and track" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/patents/trains_and_track.jpg"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;US4861306A covers the design of the rail (various style are discussed) as well as engine and railcar elements.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://patents.google.com/patent/US4861306A/en" target="_blank"&gt;US4861306A&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7/16/1987&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img alt="Turnout monorail track" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/patents/turnout.jpg"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;US5087001A covers turnouts, wyes, and crossover elements.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://patents.google.com/patent/US5087001A/en" target="_blank"&gt;US5087001A&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/21/1990&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img alt="Long straight monorail track" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/patents/long_straight.jpg"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;USD296806S covers the design of the long straight track piece.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://patents.google.com/patent/USD296806/en" target="_blank"&gt;USD296806S&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/26/1986&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img alt="Short straight monorail track" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/patents/short_straight.jpg"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;USD296803S covers the design of the short straight track piece.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://patents.google.com/patent/USD296803S/en" target="_blank"&gt;USD296803S&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/26/1986&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img alt="Large curve monorail track" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/patents/large_curve.jpg"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;USD296804S covers the design of the large curve piece.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://patents.google.com/patent/USD296804S/en" target="_blank"&gt;USD296804S&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/26/1986&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img alt="Monoswitch patent preview" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/patents/monoswitch.jpg"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;USD296805S covers the monoswitch (stop/go) track piece.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://patents.google.com/patent/USD296805S/en" target="_blank"&gt;USD296805S&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/26/1986&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img alt="Monorail track geometry" src="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/images/patents/track_geometry.jpg"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;US4726515A covers track geometry such as the layout of curves.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://patents.google.com/patent/US4726515A/en" target="_blank"&gt;US4726515A&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2/25/1987&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</content><category term="Resources"></category><category term="patents"></category></entry><entry><title>Monorail Element Map</title><link href="https://www.monorailmaniac.com/monorail-element-map.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-10-04T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-10-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>The Monorail Maniac</name></author><id>tag:www.monorailmaniac.com,2025-10-04:/monorail-element-map.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Relates monorail elements with the set(s) which included them.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Monorail Element Map&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This map relates monorail elements with the sets they appear in. Links to the relevant BrickLink pages are included.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Element&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;BrickLink Item Number&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?S=5039-1&amp;amp;name=Monorail%20Stop%20/%20Reverse%20Switch&amp;amp;category=%5BService%20Packs%5D#T=S&amp;amp;O={%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;Monorail Stop / Reverse Switch (5039)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?S=5040-1&amp;amp;name=Monorail%209V%20Motor&amp;amp;category=%5BService%20Packs%5D#T=S&amp;amp;O={%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;Monorail 9V Motor (5040)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?S=6347-1&amp;amp;name=Monorail%20Accessory%20Track&amp;amp;category=%5BTown%5D%5BClassic%20Town%5D%5BSupplemental%5D#T=S&amp;amp;O={%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;Monorail Accessory Track (6347)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?S=6399-1&amp;amp;name=Airport%20Shuttle&amp;amp;category=%5BTown%5D%5BClassic%20Town%5D%5BAirport%5D#T=S&amp;amp;O={%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;Airport Shuttle (6399)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?S=6921-1&amp;amp;name=Monorail%20Accessory%20Track&amp;amp;category=%5BSpace%5D%5BSupplemental%5D#T=S&amp;amp;O={%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;Monorail Accessory Track (6921)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?S=6990-1&amp;amp;name=Futuron%20Monorail%20Transport%20System&amp;amp;category=%5BSpace%5D%5BFuturon%5D#T=S&amp;amp;O={%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;Futuron Monorail Transport System (6990)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?S=6991-1&amp;amp;name=Monorail%20Transport%20Base&amp;amp;category=%5BSpace%5D%5BUnitron%5D#T=S&amp;amp;O={%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;Monorail Transport Base (6991)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Black Monorail Wheel Pair on Silver Axle&lt;sup id="fnref3:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=bb1171c01&amp;amp;idColor=11#T=S&amp;amp;C=11&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:11,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;bb1171c01&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Black Monorail Bogie&lt;sup id="fnref2:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2686&amp;amp;idColor=11#T=S&amp;amp;C=11&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:11,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;2686&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Black Monorail Bogie Bracket/Pivot&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2697&amp;amp;idColor=11#T=S&amp;amp;C=11&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:11,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;2697&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Black Monorail Base 4x20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2687#T=S&amp;amp;C=11&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:11,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;2687&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monorail Coupling Short&lt;sup id="fnref3:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2685a#T=S&amp;amp;C=11&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:11,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;2685a&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monorail Coupling Long&lt;sup id="fnref3:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2685b#T=S&amp;amp;C=11&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:11,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;2685b&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monorail Motor Base&lt;sup id="fnref2:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id="fnref2:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2684&amp;amp;idColor=11#T=S&amp;amp;C=11&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:11,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;2684&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monorail Motor Top&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2683monorail&amp;amp;idColor=1#T=S&amp;amp;C=1&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:1,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;2583&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monorail Motor Cover&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2619#T=S&amp;amp;C=5&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:5,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;2619&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monorail Track Monoswitch&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2772c01#T=S&amp;amp;C=9&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:9,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;2774&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monorail Track Point Left&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2890#T=S&amp;amp;C=9&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:9,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;2890&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monorail Track Point Right&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2889#T=S&amp;amp;C=9&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:9,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;2889&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monorail Track Curve Short Left&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2892#T=S&amp;amp;C=9&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:9,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;2892&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monorail Track Curve Short Right&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2891#T=S&amp;amp;C=9&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:9,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;2891&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monorail Track Curve Long&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2672#T=S&amp;amp;C=9&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:9,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;2672&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monorail Track Straight Short&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2670#T=S&amp;amp;C=9&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:9,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;2670&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monorail Track Straight Long&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2671#T=S&amp;amp;C=9&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:9,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;2671&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monorail Track Ramp Lower&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2677#T=S&amp;amp;C=9&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:9,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;2677&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Monorail Track Ramp Upper&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2678#T=S&amp;amp;C=9&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:9,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;2678&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These parts combine to form a complete bogie. The complete bogie is listed as BrickLink item number &lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2686c01#T=S&amp;amp;C=11&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:11,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;2686c01&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref2:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref3:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These parts combine to form a complete motor. The motor with short couplings is listed as BrickLink item number &lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2684c01a#T=S&amp;amp;O={%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;2684c01a&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref2:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref3:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These parts combine to form a complete motor. The motor with long couplings is listed as BrickLink item number &lt;a href="https://www.bricklink.com/v2/catalog/catalogitem.page?P=2684c01b#T=S&amp;amp;C=1&amp;amp;O={%22color%22:1,%22iconly%22:0}" target="_blank"&gt;2684c01b&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref2:3" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref3:3" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Resources"></category><category term="sets"></category><category term="parts"></category></entry></feed>